Okay today's דף *Daf* is דף ט' *Daf Tet*. We pick up
at the very top of דף ט' *Daf Tet*. We are still
going through and figuring out which קרבן korban *Korban* atones for which
thing. We basically figured out that the יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom
Kippur* one that's brought on the inner, in the Holy of Holies,
does for something that is מקדש Mikdash. וקדשיו *Mikdash V'Kodashav* based on
וכיפר על הקדש מטמאת בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael *V'Chiper Al HaKodesh MiTumot
B'nei Yisrael*. It's something that there was a knowledge at the beginning
and not at the end because it says לכל חטאתם *L'Khol Chatatam*
which means that on the one hand, it's not obligated in a
חטאת chatat *Chatat* now, but a חטאת Chatat *Chatat* would be possible
if the person would know. And יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*
of מוסף musaf *Musaf* is the reverse, based on the fact that
it links the two, מלבד חטאת Chatat הכפורים *MiLevad Chatat HaKippurim*, we
said that they both atone for מקדש Mikdash. וקדשיו *Mikdash V'Kodashav*, both
with a ידיעה yediah *Yedi'ah*. This has a ידיעה *Yedi'ah* at the
end.
This one had a ידיעה *Yedi'ah* at the beginning; this one has
a ידיעה *Yedi'ah* at the end. Okay so that's basically what we've
established and that even though they're linked, they each do their distinct
thing; they don't do the work of the other one. All right
and now we continue on top of ט' עמוד א' *Tet Amud
Aleph*. ולרבי ישמעאל דאמר אין בו ידיעה בתחילה ויש בו ידיעה בסוף
בר קרבן korban הוא *U'l'Rabbi Yishmael d'amar ein bo yedi'ah batchilah v'yesh
bo yedi'ah b'sof bar korban hu*. Now there's a רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael. *Rabbi Yishmael* who says that, which we haven't really engaged yet,
but who says that even if something, even if there was never
ידיעה בתחילה *Yedi'ah BaTchilah*, right, it says ונעלם ממנו והוא ידע ואשם
*V'Ne'elam Mimenu V'Hu Yada V'Ashem* or whatever, that he says I don't
need you to be aware initially that you touched something טמא tamei
*Tamei*. Even if somebody was, you know, oblivious initially and sinned and
then became aware, that would also be enough to bring a קרבן
korban *Korban*, which is completely reasonable. So that means he would say
you bring a קרבן Korban *Korban* in this case; you didn't need
ידיעה בתחילה *Yedi'ah BaTchilah*. So according to him that this case you
bring this קרבן Korban, *Korban*, you bring your normal personal קרבן Korban
*Korban*, what job are you going to give the יום כיפור Yom
Kippur *Yom Kippur* of מוסף musaf *Musaf*? Okay ולרבי ישמעאל דאמר אין
בו ידיעה בתחילה ויש בו ידיעה בסוף בר קרבן Korban הוא שעיר
se'ir הנעשה בחוץ על מה מכפר *U'l'Rabbi Yishmael d'amar ein bo yedi'ah
batchilah v'yesh bo yedi'ah b'sof bar korban hu, se'ir hanna'aseh bachutz al
mah m'chapper?* And what is the goat that's done outside, the מוסף
Musaf *Musaf* of יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*, what does it
atone for? על שאין בו ידיעה לא בתחילה ולא בסוף *Al she-ein
bo yedi'ah lo batchilah v'lo b'sof*. So the only thing left if
we're going to assume it's still operating in the world of מקדש
Mikdash וקדשיו *Mikdash V'Kodashav*, the only thing left would be what we've
normally assigned for רגלים Regalim *Regalim* and ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh *Rosh
Chodesh*. No knowledge בתחילה ובסוף *BaTchilah u-b'sof*. That's now going to be
the קרבן מוסף korban musaf *Korban Musaf* of יום כיפור Yom Kippur
*Yom Kippur* for רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael, *Rabbi Yishmael* because he would
say in this case the individual actually brings his own קרבן Korban
*Korban*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says האי *hai* but one minute
that שעירי הרגלים ושעירי החודשים מכפרים *se'irei ha-regalim v'se'irei ha-chodeshim m'chapper* and
that's already going to be taken care of by the goats of
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh *Rosh Chodesh* and the רגלים regalim *Regalim*, by
the goats of the מוסף Musaf *Musaf* of those days. So what
do you need the יום כיפור Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur* קרבן Korban.
*Korban* to do that? No סבר לה laHashem כרבי מאיר דאמר כל
השעירים כפרתן שוה על טמאת מקדש Mikdash וקדשיו *savar lah k'Rabbi Meir
d'amar kol ha-se'irim kapparatan shavah al tumat mikdash v'kodashav*. Yeah you're right
but so what? He holds like רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. רבי מאיר
*Rabbi Meir* in the משנה *Mishnah* says that all of them, meaning
not the one on the inside on יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom
Kippur*, that obviously has a distinct status, but everything that's brought as
a מוסף Musaf, *Musaf*, all of these, the same way רגלים regalim
*Regalim* and ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh, *Rosh Chodesh* are doing the same,
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says the יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*
מוסף Musaf, *Musaf* also does the same. They're all doing the same
function. Okay now what is that function? For רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*
it includes this, the case of not knowing in the beginning and
knowing at the end. For רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* you don't need
this; this is an individual קרבן Korban *Korban*. But basically it's okay
if we say that all of these do the same function. So
for רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* this is brought by the individual, not
knowing at the beginning and knowing at the end, and not knowing
at either stage it's done whatever מוסף Musaf *Musaf* you're dealing with,
מוסף Musaf, *Musaf* of יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur*, מוסף Musaf.
*Musaf* of רגלים regalim *Regalim*, מוסף Mussaf *Musaf* of ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh *Rosh Chodesh*, it all does the same job. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says אלא למאי הלכתא איתקש חיצון לפנימי *ela l'mai hilkheta
itkash chitzon l'pnimay?* If that's true why are we linking the מוסף
Mussaf *Musaf* יום כיפור Yom Kippur? *Yom Kippur* to the inner Holy
of Holies of יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur* right? Since basically
this is just like the ones down here according to רבי ישמעאל
*Rabbi Yishmael*. Still have to find out who stole my markers here.
I'm going to find my marker, hold on. They're going to be
all used up since people keep stealing them.
Okay
anyway so for רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* that says that all of
these do the same thing, okay that's רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* and
this is brought by the individual, what's the point where it says
מלבד חטאת chatat הכפורים *MiLevad Chatat HaKippurim*? Why are these two being
linked? Okay this one has a ידיעה *Yedi'ah*, this one does not.
What's the goal of linking them?
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אלא למאי הלכתא איתקש חיצון לפנימי
מה פנימי אינו מכפר בשאר עבירות averot? אף חיצון אינו מכפר בשאר
עבירות *l'mai hilkheta itkash chitzon l'pnimay? mah pnimay eino m'chapper b'sha'ar aveirot
af chitzon eino m'chapper b'sha'ar aveirot*. Just to tell you that you
should know the thing that this works for and then also that
these are going to work for, which is what we're going to
get to in a minute, because it just says שעיר se'ir לכפר
l'chaper, *se'ir l'chapper*, what's it atoning about? We don't know what it's
atoning for. That's true by the רגלים regalim *Regalim* and ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh *Rosh Chodesh*, even by יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur*
we don't know what the goat is atoning for, the outer goat,
the מוסף musaf *Musaf*. So because it's linked we say the same
way this is atoning for טמאת מקדש Mikdash, *Tumat Mikdash* which you
remember we know by the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* which says explicitly. Actually
should be וכפר על הקדש, right?
So the same way we know that this atones for טומאת מקדש,
Tumat Mikdash, so these atone for, this and this we're gonna see
in a minute, these all atone for טומאת מקדש Tumat Mikdash as
well. Okay, that's for רבי ישמעאל. For רבי ישמעאל, this is brought
by the individual, all of these קרבנות, korbanot, this standard קרבן Korban
מוסף of every single מוסף you ever bring is for טומאת מקדש
Tumat Mikdash that nobody ever knows about, and the link יום כיפור
Yom Kippur, is just to tell you that these מוספים musafim although
it just says in the תורה Torah that it's, you know, לכפר,
lechaper, what it actually is atoning for is atoning for what do
you call it, is atoning for טומאת מקדש. Tumat Mikdash. And the
only thing that's explicit about טומאת מקדש Tumat Mikdash is the קרבן
Korban. of יום כיפור Yom Kippur that is brought into the קדש
הקדשים. Kodesh HaKodashim.
All right, why
do you have so many קרבנות? korbanot?
Yeah, that's a really good question. I don't know. Meaning if, you
know, again, if first of all, the very fact that the גמרא
Gemara starts by, as I've said before, describing the יום כיפור Yom
Kippur. טומאת מקדש Tumat Mikdash in what, you know, in sort of
very technical sense, not in the broader sense of the טומאת מקדש,
Tumat Mikdash, which is what, you know, I've been talking about, not
in the broader sense of cleansing it from the טומאה tumah created
by sin, but cleansing it from, you know, טומאה, tumah, you know,
that was because somebody did, you know, was טמא tamei and ate
a קרבן Korban or went into the מקדש. Mikdash You know, already,
you know, you take like this very central קרבן Korban of atonement,
which is one day every year, and you make it about this
very specific sin. And then to go ahead and take that and
continue and say that's what we need the קרבנות korbanot for every
single מוסף to do, different variations of the same sin. I, you're
right, I really struggle with that. The only thing that I could
say in a response is is that it's, you know, is that
it's sort of the same idea of like, but, you know, rather
than the metaphor, rather than the broader idea that sin creates טומאה
tumah and drives out God or whatever the טומאה tumah does, right?
But it challenges the sense of the קדש. kodesh. So the טומאה
tumah that's being dealt here with the, you know, is also a
sense of like how are we, are we being properly careful with
that sense of that there's this holy place in our midst? Right?
And the פסוק pasuk says, you know, השוכן אתם בתוך טמאתם, hashochein
itam b'toch tumotam, like God dwells with us in our טומאה. tumah.
And again, even though that טומאה tumah probably means the טומאה tumah
of our imperfection and of our sin, but in the most concrete
way, that sanctity is violated, right? We are not being sensitive to
God's presence in our midst if we are going ahead and being
טמא tamei and eating קרבנות korbanot or going טמא Tamei. and entering
into the מקום המקדש. Makom HaMikdash. So it is the most concrete
way which sort of reflects the lack of sufficient sensitivity to the
idea that God can dwell among us and God can dwell in
earth and so on and God's presence and so on, and we're
not being sensitive to that and so on. So I think that
that would, you know, I would try to sort of give it
broader symbolic significance. You know, it's not just, you know, we gotta
atone for a sin, right? There's plenty of sins we gotta atone
for. But maybe the central קרבנות korbanot of atonement in the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash are about this sin because this sin reflects the
lack of proper care and sensitivity and, you know, recognizing sort of
God's, you know, what it means that there is קדש kodesh among
us. So but thank you, but yes, that is the important question
to ask: who needs all these קרבנות korbanot for, you know, this
handful of sins?
Yes. And maybe two more things. One is that we have all
the פסוקים, psukim, we don't know what to do with these פסוקים,
psukim, they have to go somewhere. Right? But two, like, you know,
if you go to whatever, Walgreens and look at the different medicines
you have for headaches and things, like somebody would walk in there
and be like, what do you need all these for?
Right, but I think the still question is why imagine walking into
Walgreens and there was 20 different medicines for coughs and no medicines
for anything else, you know? That's sort of Michael's question, right? Why
are coughs the most important thing that we need 20 medicines for?
What about runny noses? What about headaches? What about sore throats? What
about this?
What has medicines for? What?
In this metaphor. All of these things, which are the קרבנות, korbanot,
the things that are brought communally to atone for sin, right? These
are the communal קרבנות korbanot of חטאת chatat, for the ציבור, tzibur,
not that the individual brings.
And so the communal קרבנות korbanot that are brought for sin are
all brought for just one type of sin, for the טומאת מקדש
וקדשיו. Tumat Mikdash V'Kodashav. So that was the question. So that's why
I said I think that even if it's, you know, that it
sort of it because because that is the thing that most challenges
the presence of the מקדש. Mikdash, Here God has created a מקדש
Mikdash. and created a sense of divine presence and whatever and קדש
kodesh and holy things, and if you're mistreating them, you know, then
that challenges the idea that we have a מקדש Mikdash, among us.
So that's why that's the things that needs the most forms of
addressing. But that was the question that Michael was asking. Not like
why do you need so many קרבנות korbanot for one sin, but
why is
one particular...
Don't we have a system for the other things?
Yeah, but we also have a system for this. Let's say I
was מחלל שבת Mechallel Shabbat and I was never aware of it.
Who's bringing a קרבן Korban, for me for that? Let's say I
ate, I ate חלב chelev and I was aware of it, you
know, and I was aware at the beginning and not at the
end or whatever, right? All, what about every single other sin? There
are cases where I'm not yet aware of it, and nothing is,
nobody's bringing any קרבנות Korbanot for me for that.
What about the one that goes out to the desert? Does that
atone?
So for that, yes, that does atone once in the year and
so on for all the sins, that's true. So that still raises
a question, right? Which is why so many things during the year
for this sin and all the other sins get this one thing
of sending the goat over, right? The sin of טומאת מקדש Tumat
Mikdash is still being given a tremendous amount of focus and emphasis
more than anything else. So that's still the question: why? Right? So
I mean, okay, let's keep on going. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this, but yes, that is exactly the right question. Okay. על
שאין בה ידיעה בתחילה ולא בסוף שעירי רגלים ושעירי ראשי חדשים מכפרים
דברי רבי יהודה. Al she'ein bah yedi'ah batchilah v'lo basof se'irei regalim
v'se'irei roshei chodashim mechaperim divrei Rabbi Yehuda.
And this, which you don't know at the beginning or the end,
it's every single מוסף of a רגל Regel and ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh atones for טומאת מקדש Tumat Mikdash when you did not know
at the beginning or at the end. Okay. I mean, think by
the way about the fact of how the תורה Torah says that
the whole responsibility of the כהנים Kohanim is to protect the מקדש,
like ושמרו את משמרתי, veshamru et mishmarti, you know, the whole responsibility
of the כהנים Kohanim is to protect the מקדש that it does
not get defiled by the טומאה Tumah of בני ישראל and so
on. So yeah, I mean, you know, that, it is very much
about preserving the קדושה Kedushah of the place. Of course, it's also
relates to the fact that even if I didn't enter the מקדש,
I just took a קרבן, Korban I took it home to eat
with me in ירושלים Yerushalayim and I ate it when I was
טמא. Tamei, But nevertheless, again, I just think that that's what it's
about. Okay. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה? Amar
Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Yehuda? What's the reason of
רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? How's he know that your standard מוסף קרבן
Korban, atones for this? Now, you could say it's the only thing
left, right? 'Cause we have all the other variations. But the question
is not just how do you know it atones when you didn't
know at the beginning and the end, but since the תורה Torah
just generically says לכפר, you know, ושעיר
עזים אחד לכפר, vese'ir izim echad lechaper,
whatever, so since it just says to atone, maybe it atones for
other sins? What makes us, yes, this is the only thing left
on this chart, but what makes us assume that the רגלים Regalim
and ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh are for טומאת מקדש? Tumat Mikdash? Maybe
they're for plenty of other sins? So אמר קרא ושעיר עזים אחד
לחטאת להשם, Amar kra vese'ir izim echad lechatat l'Hashem,
'cause it says by ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh one goat for a
חטאת chatat, for God. So what does it mean לחטאת להשם? lechatat
l'Hashem? So the גמרא Gemara does one of its most radical theological
moves. It says חטא שאין מכיר בו אלא השם. Cheit she'ein makir
bo ela Hashem. I'm sorry, for, we're going to get to that
in a second, I jumped ahead. חטא שאין מכיר בו אלא השם.
Cheit she'ein makir bo ela Hashem. It's a חטאת chatat for חטא
cheit for השם. Hashem. השם Hashem is the only one who knows
of this sin. You, there was no knowledge at the beginning, none
at the end, God is the only one who knows. Fine. That
tells us that we're dealing with this category down here, no knowledge.
But it still doesn't tell us מקדש. How do you know it's
about טומאת מקדש? Tumat Mikdash? So the גמרא Gemara is going to
get to that. But let's, but first the גמרא Gemara has another
thing to say. ואידך דמכפר והאי מבעי ליה לכריש לקיש. V'idach demichaper
vehai mibei lei l'Reish Lakish.
One minute, you need לחטאת להשם lechatat l'Hashem to tell me the
דרשה drasha of ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, and this is, as I
said, one of the most theologically radical statements the גמרא Gemara ever
makes, דאמר ריש לקיש מה נשתנה שעיר של ראש חודש שנאמר בו
להשם? d'amar Reish Lakish mah nishtanah se'ir shel Rosh Chodesh shene'emar bo
l'Hashem?
Why does the שעיר Se'ir. of ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh. say a
sin offering for God? Normally it says for the שעיר of מוסף,
לחטאת, lechatat, for sin offering. What does it mean for a sin
offering for God? So rather than reading it as sin offering offered
to God, he's reading of it as a sin offering brought on
account of God. God has to bring a sin offering. אמר הקדוש
ברוך הוא, Amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu, God said, שעיר זה יהא כפרה,
se'ir zeh yehei kaparah, this goat should be an atonement for me
על שמיעטתי את הירח, al shemi'ateti et hayarei'ach,
because I shrunk the moon, right? The moon, at first it says
שני המאורות הגדולים, shenei hame'orot hagedolim, and then it says את המאור
הגדול לממשלת היום ואת המאור הקטן לממשלת הלילה. et hama'or hagadol l'memshelet
hayom v'et hama'or hakatan l'memshelet halaila. So it says they're both big,
then it says one is big and one is small. So the
גמרא Gemara says that the moon came and complained to God and
said, God, how can, you know, we both be co-equal? There need,
I mean, the phrase that's used is, you know, אין שני מלכים
משתמשים בכתר אחד, ein shenei melachim mishtamshim becheter echad, two kings don't
use one crown, which really should more be one king doesn't use
two crowns because God is the king in that metaphor, so it
sounds whatever, it sounds more, though, that they,
because they're לממשלת היום, l'memshelet hayom, the kings are the moon and
the sun. So we're two kings and we can't both have, you
know, one has to be in charge. You know, so I don't
know, why can't you have one king of one country, one king
of another country, one is ביום, bayom, one is בלילה? balaila? I
never fully got the metaphor. But anyway, we can't both use the
same crown. One of us has to be the head honcho. So
God says, fine, I'll make it the sun, you go ahead and
you become small. Okay? And then, so but because then God has,
and then the moon complained, I'm so small, whatever. God said, don't
worry, I'll give you the stars to make you feel better. Anyway,
so because God
had... Yes, that's a necessary dot to connect. The reason it is
about ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh because obviously you also, you know, this
it says by ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh is ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh
is when we experience the tiny size of the moon. The moon
waxes and wanes. Besides also that the moon is smaller, right, this
is when you're sort of are experiencing, you know, the, you know,
the way in which the... I mean, it is symbolic of God's
having shrunk the moon. Every year like every month the moon shrinks,
right, and then it grows back but then it shrinks, so yes,
so because of what God did here to the moon, God says
I need this atonement. Now, that is pretty crazy, right? Why does
God do, God did something wrong, God needs an atonement? So if
you look at the side here, it says זהו סוד מסודות הקבלה
ואין להבינו כפשוטו חס ושלום. Zehu sod misodot hakabbalah vein lehavino kipshuto
chas veshalom. This is one of the mystical secrets of the קבלה,
Kabbalah, God forbid that we should treat this literally. כי כל כבודה
בת מלך פנימה. Ki kol kevudah bat melech penimah. I have no
idea what that last line is supposed to mean. I have no
idea. Anyway, if you look at רש"י... Rashi... מה זה? Mah zeh?
זהו סוד? Zehu sod?
I don't know, you don't have that in your גמרא Gemara on
the right-hand margin between the גמרא Gemara and the right-hand margin? You
know, says this is one of the mystical secrets of the קבלה,
Kabbalah, don't God forbid think to treat this literally. Now, רש"י Rashi
and תוספות Tosafot are sensitive to the problem. רש"י Rashi says the
following. רש"י Rashi says
לחתאת לה', Lechatat l’Hashem, two lines down in the narrow lines, רש"י
Rashi says, I'm sorry, הביאו כפרה, Heviu kaparah, three lines down, להפיס
דעתה של לבנה. Lehafis da’atah shel levanah. Not that God says I
did anything wrong, but it's another way of making the moon feel
better. I'll say I'm sorry to make the moon feel better. Okay,
or maybe but I don't, I didn't really do anything wrong but
you know this will make... again, then you have to deal with
what does this mean that we're personifying the moon? But that was
true about the whole מדרש. Midrash. But the other thing I would
sort of say based on what I've been saying before is that
remember I said a חטאת chatat can be brought sometimes even if
you didn't do anything wrong, but just to fix something, something wrong
that was done in the world. Like the case of the person
that never knew they were Jewish and sinned, and then when they
know they find out they're Jewish they have to bring a חטאת,
chatat even if there's no blame or guilt for what that person
did. Nevertheless, something wrong happened and therefore something needs to be done
to fix it. So that's a little bit of connected to רש"י.
Rashi. This somehow fixes a problem, it might have been a necessary
problem, something that was necessary to be done, you know, but nevertheless
still like hurt was, somebody was hurt in the process and therefore
somehow you have to fix it, right, which means it doesn't matter
that it's not your fault, right, it doesn't matter that you needed
to do it, which is also important, right, because sometimes, you know,
like sometimes we have to act in a certain way and, you
know, and it's the right thing to do because there, you know,
the other choices are worse or whatever or, you know, but sometimes
even doing the right thing means people are going to get hurt
on your account. And just because you did what you did was
what you needed to do and was the right thing and there
was nothing else you could have done doesn't mean that there's not
a reality that somebody was hurt and that that's now your responsibility
to try to address the hurt that was created no matter how
right your action was. So, you know, I think that that's like
a sort of powerful way of seeing this. You know, we sometimes
question, right, about like, you know, I mean whatever, this goes to
how much you think God is involved in the world, you know,
or just you think that God creates the world and steps back
and lets everything happen. But you know, people say like, you know,
why did this person have to die, right? Why did, you know,
you know, why is there disease in the world? Like, you know,
you know, and like the, the... you know, the answer is like,
you know, this is the best of all possible worlds, God had
to create a world like this somehow for whatever reason, who gave
that, Leibniz? See, no, Voltaire wrote Candide which was a mocking of
that philosophy. Anyway, but,
but the point still is is like, you know, you could look
at things in the world and sort of say like God why
did you let this happen, right, like why, you know, and therefore
and like I think this גמרא Gemara is sort of powerful that
even if in some theoretical answer there's like it was necessary for
whatever divine reason that we're not going to understand, right, but that
doesn't mean that somehow, you know, bad things happened and they have,
and something has to be done to fix them and to, to,
you know, to address the bad that was done. So I think
that that's like the powerful sort of, you know, message here and
it's really again even saying it that way it still is, you
know, it still is like radical theologically. Okay, fine, God didn't make
a mistake, he didn't sin in the sense that he... there was
something else that could have been done, but nevertheless somebody was hurt,
you know, or the moon or whatever, bad things happened as a
result of that decision and there's a responsibility to somehow to do
something to address that. So that's yeah.
If you say spiritually, you know, we compare the Jews to the
moon, so like the punishments that the Jews have had to
appropriate...
Right, that's a nice point. The מהרש"א Maharsha makes this, this גמרא
Gemara also appears in חולין Chullin and the מהרש"א Maharsha makes that
point. one that you know is always seen as the enemy of
the Jews, is it Rome, is it Christianity, is it whatever? So,
you know, so that basically somehow, yeah, but he, I forget exactly
how he connects the dots, but basically that, you know, that the
sun represents the the nations of the world and they count by
the sun, they have a solar year, we have a lunar year.
Our fortunes wax and wane, their fortunes always seem to be doing
much, much better than the Jews. You know, and God somehow says
it is necessary that you suffer in this world because ultimately your
full dominion will be in the world to come, but in this
world it's necessary that you suffer. And that somehow, yes, this goat
is the atonement. I forget how he, how he translates that. Maybe
he says at the end of the day they'll be punished, you
know, what do you do? You slaughter the goat or something. Right,
but yes, he very much, מהרש"א Maharsha very much reads it that
way that somehow it's like a question about why, why does this
have to be our fate in the world? And whatever the answer
is that God says it's necessary, but nevertheless God says, "But I
still, I'm still responsible for the way you, for how you've suffered
and I have to do something to fix that." Right? So yes,
thank you.
Okay, so now,
תוספות Tosafot has another explanation, but it's whatever, still, we don't have
to read it. You can read it, it's one line in תוספות
Tosafot שעיר. So he says like this. Okay, so don't we need
the פסוק pasuk to teach me that and not to teach me
that it is something that nobody knows about? לה' is saying only
God knows about it. אם כן לימא קרא על ה'. im ken
leima kra al Hashem. If he just wanted to say that God
was being atoned for, as it were, then it should have said
לחטאת על ה'. lechatat al Hashem. מאי לה'? mai laHashem? To God?
לכפרה? lechapara? To tell me that it's only known by God. ואימא
כולה להאי הוא דאתא? ve'eima kula lehai hu d'ata? So maybe ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish is wrong, maybe it's all just telling you that
it's a type of sin that only God knows about.
No, אם כן לימא קרא חטאת
ה', im ken leima kra chatat Hashem, a sin offering of God.
I don't know how that would have suggested more that. מאי לה'?
mai laHashem? יתירא דל'? yeteira d'lamed? שמע מינה תרתי. shma mina tarti.
You learn both. Don't ask me exactly how it's deriving that. Anyway
fine, you get the ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish midrashic explanation and you
get the idea that nobody knows about it. But now we've got
a problem, you know, you could've anyway said obviously it's got to
be nobody knows about it, it's the only thing left on the
chart. But the question is, how do you know it has to
do with טומאת מקדש? tumat mikdash? The פסוק pasuk? just says simply
לחטאת. lechatat.
Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says: ונכפר אפילו על שאר עבירות? unichaper
afilu al shear averot? How do you know it doesn't work for
other עבירות? Why do we keep on focusing on טומאת מקדש? tumat
mikdash? תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, tana d'vei Rabbi Yishmael, תנא דבי רבי
ישמעאל: tana d'vei Rabbi Yishmael: הואיל וזה בא בזמן קבוע וזה בא
בזמן קבוע. hoil ve'ze ba bizman kavua ve'ze ba bizman kavua. So
the same way this comes at a fixed time, right, meaning this
year, the יום כיפור Yom Kippur. of מוסף, right, this comes, I
mean while it's a מוסף that comes one particular time of the
year, and this comes, right, at a fixed time, so מה זה
אינו מכפר אלא
על טומאת מקדש וקדשיו אף זה אינו מכפר אלא על טומאת מקדש
וקדשיו, ma ze eino mechaper ela al tumat mikdash vekodashav, af ze
eino mechaper ela al tumat mikdash vekodashav, which is basically like, look,
we see anyway that the types of goats that are brought for
sin offerings in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash at fixed times at
least, you know, whatever, are ones that are done, רש"י Rashi says
we're bracketing the ורמי. u'remi. Anyway, are ones that are done for
טומאת מקדש. tumat mikdash. So if we got something else that's similar,
it's a מוסף, it's a goat, it's a חטאת, chatat. we're going
to say it's doing the same thing. All right. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like
this: אשכחן שעירי ראשי חדשים, ashchan se'irei roshei chodashim, fine, that's good
by ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh, at least they come at a fixed
time. שעירי רגלים מנלן? se'irei regalim minalan? How do you know about
goats of the רגלים Regalim that come, I mean they don't come,
you don't know exactly what date, I mean they always come the
same day of the month, but they don't exactly come, you know,
the same time of the year because when the months are switches
around. וכי תימא הני נמי כי דתנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, vechi teima
hanei nami kid'tana d'vei Rabbi Yishmael, right, which is learn it from
the case of יום כיפור of מוסף. So the גמרא Gemara says:
איכא למיפרך: ika lemifrach: אי מראש חודש שכן תדיר. i mi'Rosh Chodesh,
sheken tadir. You can't learn out the רגלים Regalim from ראש חודש.
Rosh Chodesh ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh, occurs very frequently, once a month.
אי מיום הכיפורים שכן רובה כפרתה. i mi'Yom HaKippurim, sheken ruba kaparta.
You can't learn it out from anything done on יום כיפור. יום
כיפור's a day where a lot of atonement is given out. So
maybe, so רש"י, Rashi, so the way רש"י Rashi frames the question,
it's the following, it's like maybe the רגלים Regalim, don't have, are
only atone for lighter sins, for something that's let's say לאו חייב
כרת. lav chayav karet. Maybe they don't atone for the weighty sin
of טומאת מקדש. tumat mikdash. Why should I say that? Because it
is true that ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh. and יום כיפור atone for
this weighty sin of טומאת מקדש, tumat mikdash, but they have extra
weight going with them to the beginning. יום כיפור, you know, has
a lot of atonement in general, ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh is very
regular, but maybe these רגלים Regalim that are less frequent, you know,
maybe they shouldn't atone for as weighty of a sin. That's the
way רש"י Rashi reads the גמרא's Gemara question. So the גמרא Gemara
says: וכי תימא *vechi teima* one minute, if you say that, הגמינא
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh, מיום הכיפורים *hagamina Rosh Chodesh mi-Yom ha-Kippurim*? But
how do we learn ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh *Rosh Chodesh* from יום
כיפור *Yom Kippur*? יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, you know, at the end
of the day, how do we learn anything from יום כיפור *Yom
Kippur*? יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* does stuff because it's a day filled
with atonement. How do we learn, you know, so if you could
learn ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh *Rosh Chodesh* from יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*,
let's learn the רגלים regalim *Regalim* from יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לא פרכינן *lo parchinnan*, we didn't ask
the same question. התם *hatam* כפרה מכפרה כתיבא *kapara mikapara ketiva*. Now
there it already says לחטאת l'chatat, להשם L'Hashem *le-chatat la-Hashem*. Right, we
already had the להשם *la-Hashem*. And the להשם *la-Hashem* already told us
what type of way it was working. This is coming as an
atonement for all things that only God knows about. So the פשט
*pshat* of that לחטאת להשם *le-chatat la-Hashem* by ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh
*Rosh Chodesh*, I would have applied it to all sins in the
world that I don't, that nobody knows about other than God. That's
how I would have applied it. So I already know it has
a powerful atonement. And then גילוי מילתא בעלמא הוא *gilluy milta be-alma
hu*. And then when it, what I, so what do I learn
from יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*? What I learn from יום כיפור *Yom
Kippur* is it's not all things in the world. It's just about
טומאת מקדש Tum'at Mikdash. *tumat mikdash*.
Okay, so the way, the way we're saying it is like this:
by ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh. *Rosh Chodesh* it says לחטאת להשם *le-chatat
la-Hashem*.
And the להשם *la-Hashem* basically means since it's not saying what sins,
I would have said all sins that only,
that only God knows about, okay? That only God knows. אין בה
ידיעה ein ba yediah. לא בתחילה ולא בסוף *ein ba yedia lo
be-techilla ve-lo ba-sof*. Comes along, so I would have said all sins.
Comes along יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* and says wait, wait, wait, wait.
You know, it's even יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* which is a lot
of atonement only works for טומאת מקדש Tum'at Mikdash, *tumat mikdash*. So
if even יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* only works for טומאת מקדש Tum'at
Mikdash. *tumat mikdash*, this also only works for טומאת מקדש tum'as mikdash,
*tumat mikdash*. So יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*'s coming and limiting the scope
of ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh *Rosh Chodesh*. That you're able to do.
But by the רגלים regalim *Regalim* it just says לחטאת *le-chatat*. So
I have no idea what the scope is, no hint to what
the scope is. Maybe it should only be for very light sins,
maybe it shouldn't even work for טומאת מקדש tum'as mikdash *tumat mikdash*.
And I can't say learn from יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* because now
יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* will be expanding it. It'll be saying no,
this works even for a serious sin of טומאת מקדש tum'as mikdash,
*tumat mikdash*. Maybe not. Maybe that's only true on יום כיפור *Yom
Kippur* that has a lot of atonement going for it. So this
is too vague and since it's too vague, I can't, you know,
this seemed to say it works for everything, every single sin that
only God knows about. And יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* says no, no,
no, not so much. This is very vague. So I can't learn
out from, from יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* to say that it has
the weight to atone for טומאת Tum'at מקדש *tumat mikdash*. You know,
so, maybe it's only for, you know, maybe it's only for very
light sins. How do I learn it out? Yeah.
And the reason that we didn't go let's say, all right, well,
let's learn יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* from ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh. *Rosh
Chodesh* the other way around. Well, ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh. *Rosh Chodesh*
is expansion.
We already יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* we already got from מטומאות בני
ישראל *mi-tumat bnei Yisrael*.
Right, that's what I'm saying, because of that.
All right, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, okay, אבל הכא איכא
למימר כולה מילתא לא גמרינן *aval hacha ika leimeimar kula milta lo
gamrinan*. Since you can't learn the whole thing, you can't learn if
it's very vague, how are you supposed to know what it means?
אלא כדאמר רבי חמא בר חנינא *ela kide-amar Rabbi Chama bar Chanina*
שעיר ושעיר *sa'ir ve-sa'ir*. The extra ו vav *vav* ושעיר אחד לכפר
*ve-sa'ir echad le-chaper*. Okay, which is what it says by,
you know, where it says what it says, let me find the
source where רש"י *Rashi* says וכתיב ושעיר *ve-chtiv ve-sa'ir*, right, by all
of the מוספים *Musafim* it says ושעיר *ve-sa'ir*. So, so it's the
ו vav *vav*, it's this goat of, of the other רגלים *Regalim*
is like the goat of ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh *Rosh Chodesh*. So
the same way the goat of ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh *Rosh Chodesh*
is for טומאת מקדש *tumat mikdash*, the רגלים *Regalim* is also for
the טומאת מקדש *tumat mikdash*. הכא נמי שעיר ושעיר *hacha nami sa'ir
ve-sa'ir*. Okay, so somehow the ושעיר אחד לחטאת *ve-sa'ir echad le-chatat* which
is what it says by the רגלים *Regalim* connects it to ראש
חודש Rosh Chodesh *Rosh Chodesh*. So once we've decided that's what ראש
חודש Rosh Chodesh. *Rosh Chodesh* is doing, we've decided that's what the
רגלים *Regalim* are doing. Okay. והקיש שעיר רגלים ושעיר ראשי חדשים *ve-hikish
sa'ir regalim ve-sa'ir rashei chodashim*. מה שעיר ראשי חדשים אינו מכפר אלא
על שאין בה ידיעה לא בתחילה ולא בסוף al she'ein ba yediah
lo batchila velo basof, *ma sa'ir rashei chodashim eino mechaper ela al
she-ein ba yedia lo be-techilla ve-lo ba-sof*, אף שעיר רגלים אינו מכפר
אלא על שאין בה ידיעה לא בתחילה ולא בסוף *af sa'ir regalim
eino mechaper ela al she-ein ba yedia lo be-techilla ve-lo ba-sof*. So
what we learn from the link is both that it's טומאת מקדש
*tumat mikdash* and that it's something that you only know about beginning
and end. Okay. So, how, what, now we have filled out the
whole chart. יום כיפור בפנים *Yom Kippur bifnim* is טומאת מקדש *tumat
mikdash* because it says וכפר על הקודש מטומאות בני ישראל *ve-chiper al
ha-kodesh mi-tumot bnei Yisrael*. And we know it's that you don't have
ידיעה בסוף *yedia ba-sof* because it says לחטאת *le-chatat*, something that's not
a חטאת chatat *chatat* yet but it could become a חטאת chatat
*chatat* for the individual if they become aware at the end and
they would go up here and bring this. יום כיפור המוסף *Yom
Kippur ha-musaf* we learn because it says מלבד חטאת chatat הכפורים *milvad
chatat ha-kippurim*. They're linked together. So they both work on טומאת מקדש
*tumat mikdash* and both work with some form of ידיעה *yedia*. This
has ידיעה *yedia* at the beginning, this has ידיעה *yedia* at the
end. רגלים וראש חודש *Regalim ve-Rosh Chodesh* because ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh
*Rosh Chodesh* says לחטאת להשם *le-chatat la-Hashem*, we know that there's no
ידיעה בתחילה ובסוף *yedia be-techilla u-ve-sof*.
לחטאת להשם *le-chatat la-Hashem*.
Since I'm doing all of these, okay, fine.
לחטאת
להשם *le-chatat la-Hashem*.
That tells me no ידיעה בתחילה ובסוף *yedia be-techilla u-ve-sof*. How do
you know... So how do you know the that it's only טומאת
מקדש because it basically is linked to יום כיפור? Okay, it says,
does it actually quote a פסוק? Yes, that's right. Plus, you know,
just sort of some type of a parallel to יום כיפור, okay,
that sort of limits the scope and tells you טומאת that it's
טומאת מקדש. Good. What was that
part because of that parallel? The parallel to יום כיפור, this is
a חטאת chatat that is טומאת מקדש, this is a חטאת chatat
that's טומאת מקדש. Okay. The להשם just tells you אין בה ידיעה.
That's ראש חודש, and then we go from ראש חודש to רגלים
because it says it says this year. And the ו vav basically
allows you to make the, you know, to make the connection of
the two. Okay.
What does that X in the middle between תחילה tchilla and סוף?
sof? Oh, נעלם. ne'elam.
Yeah, that's נעלם, ne'elam, but that's confusing, if you know. This is
where your ידיעה is. There's always נעלם ne'elam in the middle.
טוב, Tov, there's no נעלם. ne'elam.
All right, I understand. Okay here.
By the way, no, this bit's terrible. נעלם, ne'elam, wait a
minute.
Okay, anyway, fine. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. איבעיא
להו. Ibayu lehu. Now, let's work within this position. כי אמר רב
יהודה השאין בידיעה לא בתחילה ולא בסוף, Ki amar Rav Yehuda hashain
beyediah lo batchila velo basof, when רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says that
on on the רגלים and ראש חודש, it works if you don't
know at the beginning or at the
end, הני מילי בחטא שאין סופו להיוודע, hani milei bechet she'ain sofo
lehivada, is that only a חטא chet that nobody in the end
will know about? Meaning להיוודע? lehivada? Yes, thank you. That's the proper
grammar, להיוודע, lehivada, okay, אבל בחטא שסופו להיוודע כמי שיש בה ידיעה
בסוף דמי, aval bechet shesofo lehivada k'mi sheyesh ba yediah basof dami,
let's say it's a חטא chet that even though you completely don't
know about it, somebody else knows about it. Somebody saw you do
it, and therefore that per- it's quite possible that eventually you will
find out about it. Now, because that person will inform you. And
if you find out about it now, you won't still bring your
own sin offering because you will only have knowledge at the end,
then you will qualify for the sin offering up here of מוסף
of יום כיפור, right? If somebody tells you what you did, you're
never retroactively going to have known before the sin. But if somebody
tells you what you're did, you'd go up to this category. So
the question is, if you are right now down here, okay, if
you are right now down here and it's a type of a
חטא chet that could go up here, is this going to atone
for you?
Or is this one the one that's going to atone for you?
What's category are you in? Okay.
אבל בחטא
שסופו להיוודע כמי שיש בה ידיעה בסוף דמי, aval bechet shesofo lehivada
k'mi sheyesh ba yediah basof dami, it's like you already know at
the end, ושעיר נעשה בחוץ יום הכיפורים מכפר, v'sayir na'aseh bachutz Yom
HaKippurim mechaper, and that's taking care of by the מוסף of יום
כיפור and יום כיפור. או דילמא אפילו חטא שסופו להיוודע השתא מיהו
חטא שאינו מכיר בו אלא השם קרינן ביה, O dilma afilu chet
shesofo lehivada hashta mihu chet she'aino makir bo ella HaShem karinu bei,
or even if at the end it might get known, right now
the only one who knows about it is God, and you're taken
care of by the רגלים and ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and ראש
חודש. תא שמע כמאן דתניא, Ta shma k'man detanya, we דתניא detania
ברייתא, baraita, על שאין בה ידיעה לא בתחילה ולא בסוף, if you
don't know at the beginning or at the end, okay, בחטא שסופו
להיוודע, bechet shesofo lehivada, and similarly a חטא chet that eventually will
be known about, but is not known about right now, שעירי רגלים
ושעירי ראש חודשים מכפרים דברי רבי יהודה. se'irei regalim v'se'irei rosh chodashim
mechaperin divrei Rabbi Yehuda. That's still taken care of by ראש חודש
and the רגלים, okay, which makes sense. Right now that's the state
that you're in. So then would they have to when they know
about it then bring a variable
offering? No, because because you will never retroactively know at the beginning.
Even when you know about it, you'll find out that you sinned,
you won't have known about it beforehand sinning. The only person that
will ever bring it is this guy up here. So this is
so this is the only one that when you know at the
beginning. So the only one that you don't now have to bring
this but could wind up bringing later is this guy, because this
guy knew at the beginning and he doesn't know now but he
could know later. That's why the גמרא said that you learn out
from the word לחטאת, that it could become this קורבן. korban. But
either of these two guys, you won't find out something retroactively, right?
So these two will never be able to bring this קורבן. korban.
Because if you didn't know before you sinned, you'll never retroactively know
before you sinned. The most you can do is know now.
Right. Okay, you know, just one broader thing I was just thinking
about is, you know, in some ways, I guess we'll kind of,
you know, say that the, for lack of a better word, the
fixation on טומאת מקדש וקדשיו Tum'at Mikdash v'Kodashav for
all these קורבנות korbanot in some ways makes it more comforting to
us these days because if you had so many קורבנות korbanot for
for everything and now we don't have it, you know, now what
do we do? We're rudderless. But if it was all for this
to begin with, טומאת
מקדש וקדשיו.
Tum'at
Mikdash v'Kodashav.
Yeah, that's a good point. And then we don't have a בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Yeah, but but you had all your personal קורבנות
korbanot that you could have brought for your personal sins, but I
hear your point. Okay, so the גמרא says like this: רבי שמעון
אומר שעירי רגלים מכפרים אבל לא שעירי ראש חודש. Rabbi Shimon omer
se'irei regalim mechaperin aval lo se'irei rosh chodesh. So רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says, רגלים is doing this, and now for רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon he brings down
ראש חודש, and ראש חודש operates for him on a totally separate,
I guess I should use my black thing, for him ראש חודש
operates in, I mean it's still related to the מקדש, but it's
No, they got stolen. Whatever. I'll get one. Anyway, but this is
we're now dealing with רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. Okay, eating a קרבן
טמא. Korban Tamei. Not eating when you are טמא, Tamei, but eating
a קרבן טמא. Korban Tamei. That's what he says ראש חודש does.
Okay, so now we're going to have two questions.
And by the way, did you know and was there?
Yeah, so he doesn't even get into presumably all variations. Well, the
point is here's the point. Excuse me. Eating a קרבן טמא, Korban
Tamei, even if you, you know, had all these things, you know
at the beginning, you forgot, you whatever, you never normally bring a
personal קרבן Korban for it. It's not a חיוב חטאת chiyuv chatat
because it's not a חיוב כרת. chiyuv karet. The only thing you
bring a חטאת chatat is something you're חייב כרת. chayav karet. Once
the קרבן Korban became טמא, Tamei all of these your טמא Tamei
and you violated the קודש, Kodesh, you violated the קרבן. korban. So
because of that, that the קודש Kodesh and the קרבן korban. are
where they should be and you violated it, it's a very heavy
sin, it's a כרת karet and therefore you could have to bring
a personal חטאת. chatat If the קרבן became was טמא tamei, and
you ate it, you would be a לאו, lav, you'd get מלקות
malkot I guess if you got warning and you did it במזיד,
bemeizid, but if you did it בשוגג beshogeg there's no atonement. It's
like any other לאו lav that there's no חטאת chatat for. Okay,
so the only חטאת chatat that's brought, right, is the one that's
brought on ראש חודש. Otherwise you would never personally bring one. Which
raises an interesting question: would it even deal with a case במזיד?
bemeizid? Presumably not. Presumably we're still בשוגג. beshogeg. But it doesn't matter
which level of knowledge we're dealing with because there's never a personal
קרבן. So any degree of ignorance or whatever, that's being taken care
of
by the שמעון Shimon here.
Okay. Do you mind?
And then I can put him back with the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma over here
and add in the ראש חודש so we know. Because
you know, this is a good chart to have. I understand.
I'll try to get other
colors. Okay.
Alright. So now it says like this: אמר אלעזר אמר הושעיה מהי
טעמא דרבי שמעון? Amar Elazar amar Oshaya mai taama deRebbi Shimon? מהי
טעמא Mai taama of רבי שמעון? Rebbi Shimon? אמר קרא: Amar kra:
ואותה נתן לכם לשאת את עוון העדה. Ve'osah nasan lachem laseis es
avon ha'eidah.
This is when משה Moshe tells to אהרן, Aharon, hey, you guys,
why did you do that? That's what משה Moshe said, you guys.
Why do you burn this חטאת on the day of the מילואים?
miluim? You're supposed to eat it. And now which חטאת is he
talking about? Is it the חטאת of the מילואים? miluim? According to
the גמרא it was also ראש חודש ניסן, Rosh Chodesh Nisan, so
you had the חטאת that נחשון Nachshon brought for the נשיאים, Nesi'im,
and you had the חטאת of ראש חודש. So the גמרא decides
elsewhere that it's the חטאת of ראש חודש. And משה Moshe says:
Why did you bring it? You should have eaten it. And now
it describes what the function of that חטאת was: ואותה נתן לכם
לשאת את עוון העדה. Ve'osah nasan lachem laseis es avon ha'eidah.
This is here to carry atonement for the sin of
the congregation. והאי קרא בראש חודש כתיב. Ve'hai kra beRosh Chodesh ketiv.
Okay, so that was a ראש חודש goat. Now how do we
know what that means, עוון העדה? avon ha'eidah? ויליף עוון עוון מציץ.
Veyalif avon avon miTzitz.
We learn it out from the ציץ, Tzitz, from the, you know,
forehead plate of the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. נאמר כאן עוון ונאמר
להלן עוון. Ne'emar kan avon vene'emar lehalan avon. It says there too:
ונשא אהרן את עוון הקדשים, Venasa Aharon es avon hakodashim, the sins
of the sacrifices. Now there we understand that what the ציץ Tzitz
does is that it means if the blood of a sacrifice or
the fats or the meat became טמא, tamei. that because he was
wearing his ציץ Tzitz on his forehead, or even if he wasn't
wearing it, because it was around, therefore the sacrifice is still valid.
If something became טמא. tamei, That's the point of that. Not to
atone for sin, this is exactly a difference we're going to make.
It's עוון הקדשים, avon hakodashim, not עוון העדה. avon ha'eidah. I'm jumping
a little ahead, but it's a very clear way of understanding the
difference. Okay, by the ציץ Tzitz it means the sacrifice was somehow
defiled, it became טמא, tamei. but because of the ציץ, Tzitz, it's
still a כשר קרבן, kasher Korban, עוון הקדשים. avon hakodashim. But the
scenario is the קרבן became טמא. tamei, So here what we're saying
is the קרבן became טמא, tamei, but the problem isn't the question
of the validity of the קרבן, it's that then you ate it.
And did you do a sin? So now the issue is עוון
העדה. avon ha'eidah. So they're both about a קרבן that became טמא,
tamei, okay, but, alright, but you know the difference is,
right, running out of space to draw stuff. Okay anyway the difference
is right here's your קרבן, here it became טמא, tamei. okay so
there's two things that can happen to it right one is you
know here you are right you know you could eat it I'll
draw you with a big mouth open
okay you can eat it right or you could go ahead and
draw my little altar there and you could sprinkle the blood onto
the onto the altar okay so this קרבן so so but they're
both the same scenario that the קרבן became
טמא. tamei Okay, that says that that is okay. Check, even though
the קרבן *Korban* was טמא *Tamei*, it's okay. Okay, and the ראש
חודש *Rosh Chodesh* says is מכפר *Mechaper* on your eating it. So
we know that because they both say עוון *Avon*, we're dealing about
the same scenario, but this is עוון הקדשים *Avon Hakodashim* and this
is עוון העדה *Avon
Ha'eida*, dealing with two variations of what happens with a קרבן *Korban*
that becomes טמא *Tamei*. All right, so, מה להלן טומאת
בשר אף כאן טומאת
בשר *Mah lehalan tumat basar af kan tumat basar*. אי מה להלן
עולין *Ei mah lehalan olin*, maybe there what the ציץ *Tzitz* does
is it means that it's כשר *Kosher* as a קרבן *Korban*, אף
כאן עולין *af kan olin*, here too it's what's put up on
the מזבח *Mizbeach* and the point is that it's כשר *Kosher* as
a קרבן *Korban*. No, עוון העדה כתיב *Avon Ha'eida ketiv*. No, no,
here it's the sin of the people, not the status of the
קרבן *Korban*. מכדי מגמיר גמירי מהדדי *Michdei migmar gamiri mehadadei*, one minute,
but we're learning them from one another because they're linked by the
word עוון *Avon*. So why don't we say that each one does
double duty, that the similar question as he's asked before. נכפר דראש
חודש אדידיה ואדציץ *Mechaper deRosh Chodesh adidei ve'adTzitz*. Let the ראש חודש
*Rosh Chodesh* one atone for people who ate טמא *Tamei* stuff and
let it also validate a קרבן *Korban* that was brought when it
was טמא *Tamei*. Now, the problem is who needs it to do
that? That's only once a month; the ציץ *Tzitz* is all the
time around. Why would you need the ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* thing
to validate the קרבן *Korban*? So the גמרא *Gemara* says, נפקא מינה
להיכא דנשבר הציץ *Nafka mina leheicha denishbar haTzitz*. Let's say the ציץ
*Tzitz* broke, okay, because it doesn't have to actively be worn by
אהרן *Aharon*, but it has to be around. So if the ציץ
*Tzitz* isn't functional,
I understand, maybe the קרבן *Korban* of ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* does
its job. No, אמר קרא עוון *Amar kra Avon*, sin, in the
singular. עוון אחד הוא נושא ואינו נושא שני עוונות *Avon echad hu
nosei ve'eino nosei shenei avonot*. לשאת את עוון העדה *Laseit et avon
ha'eida*. It only does one function, one type of a sin: the
sin of eating the קרבן *Korban*, not the status of the קרבן
*Korban*. Okay, ונכפר ציץ אדידיה ואדראש חודש *Venechaper Tzitz adidei ve'adRosh Chodesh*?
Okay, now we'll flip the question. Let the ציץ *Tzitz* do double
duty, since they're linked. Let the ציץ *Tzitz* work both to make
the קרבן *Korban* valid and to atone for people's sin when they
eat טמא קרבנות *Tamei Korbanot*. ונפקא מינה *Venafka mina*, it's easier to
find where this would matter, לטומאה דאירע בין זה לזה *Letumah de'ira
bein zeh lazeh*, אדידיה ואדראש חודש *adidei ve'adRosh Chodesh*, ונפקא מינה לטומאה
דאירע בין זה לזה *venafka mina letumah de'ira bein zeh lazeh*. People
that are eating טמא קרבנות *Tamei Korbanot* before you get around to
the ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh*, right, the ציץ *Tzitz* will atone for
you if you ate a טמא קרבן tamei korban, *Tamei Korban*. אמר
קרא אותה otah, *Amar kra Otah*, it, is נתנה לכם *nasan lachem*.
אותה נושא עוון העדה ואין אחר נושא עוון *Otah nosei avon ha'eida
ve'ein acher nosei avon*. No, so again, the word 'it' by the
ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* is עוון *Avon* says it only does one
job, and אותה *Otah*, this does this one job, nothing else does
this one job. Okay, so the ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* only does
the sin of the people, the sin of eating קרבנות טמא *Korbanot
Tamei*, and nothing else does its job. Yes.
So we learned all this from עוון הקדשים *Avon Hakodashim* that it
somehow has to do with an eating. Why can't it...
no, עוון הקדשים *Avon Hakodashim* that has to do with טמא קרבנות
*Tamei Korbanot*.
Right, but why can't it be that like
you inadvertently had a pimple or something and that's עוון הקדשים *Avon
Hakodashim* too? Why it has to be...
well, that's just a general question about how do you know that's
what the ציץ *Tzitz* is about. But so we're going to...
you're right, we're just assuming that. How do you know the ציץ
*Tzitz* is about... yeah, I don't want to... I mean, whatever, we
have to go see that סוגיא *sugya*, I don't want to get
into that, we're just taking that for granted now. אמר רב אשי
אמר קרא הכא עוון העדה *Amar Rav Ashi amar kra hacha Avon
Ha'eida*. העדה ולא קדשים *Ha'eida velo kodashim*. Okay, the way we know
it doesn't do double duty is from the word, and רש"י *Rashi*
says it's from the ה' *Heh*, עוון העדה *Avon Ha'eida*. It only
does the thing of the people, nothing else. וכתיב התם *Uchetiv hatam*,
and there it's written by the ציץ *Tzitz*, it says עוון הקדשים
*Avon Hakodashim*. קדשים ולא עדה *Kodashim velo eida*. So that's how you
know that each one only does its own job. Okay. אשכחן ראש
חודש דמכפר אבשר דנאכל בטומאה *Ashkachan Rosh Chodesh demichaper a'basar dena'achal betumah*.
Great, now you've got ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* doing this special new
thing. How do you know, going back to this, how do you
know what the רגלים *Regalim* do? Okay, because remember back here we
learned the רגלים *Regalim* because they were linked to ראש חודש *Rosh
Chodesh*. But now ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* is different. So how do
you know at all what the רגלים *Regalim* do? שעיר רגלים דמכפר
על שאין בידיעה לא בתחילה ולא בסוף *Seirei Regalim demichaper al she'ein
beyedia lo vetchila velo vesof*, and more than just also that you
don't know beginning and end, how do you know it even works
on מקדש וקדשיו *Mikdash vekodashav*? מנלן *Menalan*, where do you know it
from? כדאמר רבי חמא בר רבי חנינא שעיר וזה שעיר *Kede'amar Rabbi
Chama bar Rabbi Chanina Seir vezeh Seir*. הכא נמי שעיר וזה שעיר
*Hacha nami Seir vezeh Seir*. So like we said before, it's the
ו' *Vav*, except the problem with the ו' *Vav* is that they're
doing different things. This is on טמא קרבנות *Tamei Korbanot*, this is
when you're טמא *Tamei* and you enter into the בית המקדש *Beis
Hamikdash*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, all right, but you know, close
enough. Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* says, ואתקיש שעיר רגלים לשעיר ראש
חודש *Ve'atkish Seirei Regalim leSeirei Rosh Chodesh*. מה שעיר דראש חודש במילתא
דקודש מכפר *Mah Seir deRosh Chodesh bemilta dekodesh mechaper*, the same way
by ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* we know it has to do with
some type of a sin relating to, you know, holy things, אף
שעיר רגלים במילתא דקודש מכפרי *af Seirei Regalim bemilta dekodesh mechafrei*. So
same by the רגלים *Regalim*, some type of a קודש kodesh. *kodesh*
thing. וכי תימא נכפר אדר"ח *Vechi teima nechaper ad'Rosh Chodesh*, okay. Maybe
they do the exact same thing. Maybe both the רגלים and ראש
חודש work for somebody who ate a טמא קרבן. No, האמרינן ha'amrinan
אותה, אותה נושא עון ואין אחר נושא עון. otah nosei avon v'ein
acher nosei avon. No, we already learned that only ראש חודש does
its job, nothing else does its job. Okay, וניחא תימא נכפרי אדיומא
דכיפורים. v'nicha teima n'chapperi ad yoma d'kippurim. Okay, so fine. So the
ו tells us that this works on טומאת מקדש, something related to
קודש. kodesh. It's not the טמא קרבן, that's covered. Something related to
קודש. kodesh. And this is the only available role, row. This is
the only thing that doesn't have something plugged in. But wait, before
you plug it into here, maybe it's doing double duty with something
higher up on the list. How do you know to plug it
in over here? So the גמרא says וכי תימא נכפרי אדיומא
דכיפורי, v'chi teima n'chapperi ad yoma d'kippuri, האמרינן ha'amrinan אחת בשנה, achas
bashanah, כפרה זו לא תהא אלא אחת בשנה. kapparah zo lo tehei
ella achas bashanah. No, the words אחת achas and אחת בשנה achas
bashanah tell you these two do their own thing and nothing else
does what they do. So nothing else does, these are the, these
rows are reserved, right? You go to a whatever, you go to
a concert or something, these rows are reserved, okay? These do their
own distinct thing, nothing else gets to do their job. So we've
got this down here, okay, that's doing this. Nothing gets to do
this job. Nothing gets to do this job. רגלים is related to
קודש. The only thing left to do is to plug it into
this row. It's טומאת מקדש when nobody knows at the beginning and
at the end. So okay, אה מאי מכפרי? a mai mechappri? So
what's left? אי אית ביה ידיעה בתחילה ויש ביה ידיעה בסוף, ei
is beih yedi'ah b'techillah v'yesh beih yedi'ah b'sof, if it's a case
where you knew at the beginning and at the end and you
forgot in the middle, האי בר קרבן הוא. hai bar korban hu.
So then the individual bring a קרבן. אי אית ביה ידיעה בתחילה
ואין ביה ידיעה בסוף, ei is beih yedi'ah b'techillah v'ein beih yedi'ah
b'sof, you know, you knew at the beginning and not at the
end, האי שעיר הנעשה בפנים ביום הכיפורים תולה. hai sa'ir hana'aseh bifnim
b'Yom HaKippurim toleh. That's done by the inner goat of יום כיפור.
אי אין ביה ידיעה בתחילה ויש ביה ידיעה בסוף, ei ein beih
yedi'ah b'techillah v'yesh beih yedi'ah b'sof, if it is a case about
not knowing at the beginning and knowing at the end, האי שעיר
הנעשה בחוץ ביום הכיפורים מכפר. hai sa'ir hana'aseh bachutz b'Yom HaKippurim mechapper.
That's done by
the מוסף of ראש חודש. על כרחך אינו מכפר אלא על שאין
בה ידיעה לא בתחילה ולא בסוף. al korchacha einu mechapper ella al
she'ein bah yedi'ah lo b'techillah v'lo b'sof. The only thing left is
this row when you didn't know beginning and end. So for רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, he has ראש חודש doing its separate thing. The
ו tells you that רגלים are at least related to טומאת מקדש,
and the only thing left for them is this, is this case,
and that's where we plug that in. Okay, we will end with
this for today. There you go.